New York Inventories 1680-1848 (bulk 1726-1844) MS 450.2
New-York Historical Society
New York Inventories, 1680-1848 (bulk 1726-1844)
New-York Historical Society
MS 450.2
6 Linear feet 6 Boxes (5 Oversize)
Scope and Contents
This collection is composed of estate inventories and related documents for individuals hailing from New York City proper, as well as outlying counties and towns. There are a small number of exceptions in which persons came from Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Cumberland County, NY (now Vermont), and Spain.
Each inventory is an itemized list of personal property made upon a death for use in the settlement of the deceased's estate. Information typically recorded is name, residence, date, identity of the appraiser(s), and a monetary appraisal for each entry. In certain instances, the occupation of the deceased is noted; where it is not, this may sometimes be inferred from the contents of the inventory. A variety of occupations are represented, including various smiths, carpenter, cordwainer, farmer, mariner, grocer, shoemaker, clerk, merchant, doctor, baker, mason, and distiller.
The inventories are perhaps most useful in their reflection of the material culture of the period. The inventories are extensive, and record both valued pieces and everyday household goods, including decorative arts and furniture, kitchenware, linens, clothing, tools, personal effects, and livestock. Of particular note is the rather frequent appearance of slaves. Inventories typically show the name and sex of each slave as well as their assessed value.
Provenance
The majority of the collection came as a donation from James Wilbur in the early twentieth century, although some appear to have been added subsequently. Wilbur's purchase was possible after the Hall of Records de-accessioned the inventories while moving from the New Gaol to its present location in 1902.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Inventories that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format. The reels are available via Interlibrary Loan.
Access to some inventories not on microfilm is restricted due to the condition of the original. Please contact the Curator of Manuscripts if access is required.
Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into individual series of filmed, un filmed and oversize inventories. Within each series, the documents are arranged alphabetically by the surname of the deceased. Inventories on microfilm are also arranged in this way.
Estate inventories.; Material culture -- New York (State).; Decedents' estates -- New York (State); New York (State) -- Social life and customs.
- Series 1: Microfilmed Inventories, 1711-1815, undated (Box 2, Box 1, Box 3, Box 4)
  Scope and Content
  With only a few exceptions, the inventories in this series are documented in three lists published at various times. To consult these lists, see the Manuscript Department reference staff.
  - Filmed Inventories, A, 1728-1785 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Filmed Inventories, B – Be, 1727-1785 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Filmed Inventories, Be-Bro, 1733-1785 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Filmed Inventories, Bru-By, 1728-1815 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Filmed Inventories, C, 1724- 1785, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Filmed Inventories D-E, 1711- 1785, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Filmed Inventories F-G, 1717-1785 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Filmed Inventories H, 1726-1804 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Filmed Inventories J-K, 1726-1785 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Filmed Inventories L, 1727-1785 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Filmed Inventories M, 1726-1785 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Filmed Inventories N, 1731-1785 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Filmed Inventories P, 1726-1785 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Filmed Inventories Q, R, 1727-1784 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Filmed Inventories S-Sta, 1729-1789 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Filmed Inventories Ste-Sw, 1732-1796 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Filmed Inventories T-U, 1723-1785 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Filmed Inventories V, 1727-1785 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Filmed Inventories W-Williams, 1727-1785 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Filmed Inventories Willis – Wytt, 1726-1783, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Filmed Inventories Y, 1728-1765 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Unfilmed Inventories, 1680-1911 (Box 5)
  The documents contained within this series do not appear on the microfilm. A list of the names of the deceased can be obtained from the Manuscript Department reference staff.
  Please note that some inventories are in extremely fragile condition and may require permission to be consulted.
  - Unfilmed Inventories, A-B, 1712-1841 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Unfilmed Inventories, C-G, 1718-1911 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Unfilmed Inventories, H, 1785-1839 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Unfilmed Inventories, J-K, 1680 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Unfilmed Inventories, M-O, 1799-1841 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Unfilmed Inventories, P-R, 1797-1842 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Unfilmed Inventories, S-W, 1706-1843, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fragments and Unidentified Inventories, 1732-1766 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Oversize Inventories, 1721-1797 (Box 6)
  - Oversize Inventories B-T, 1722-1797 (Box 6, Folder 1)